Hi, this is Dr. Hallie
Zweibel, and today
we're going to be
talking about calcium,
magnesium, and phosphate
electrolyte disorders.
By the end of the
session, you'll be able to
outline calcium regulation
and dysregulation,
phosphate regulation
and magnesium regulation
and dysregulation.
When we talk about
calcium, we want to figure
out where the calcium
is within the body.
So about 40% is bound to
albumin, so that calcium
is tied up and not
physiologically active.
15% is going to be complex with
citrate, sulfates,
or phosphates.
So again, not very
physiologically important.
What is physiologically
important is the half to
45% of calcium within
the body that's ionized.
This is free calcium. And
free calcium is really
the important calcium in
terms of our physiology.
What you're seeing here is
a schematic illustration
of calcium, and how
the ECF concentration
of calcium is kept
between one to two grams.
So calcium, it's in all
different parts of the
body, we get it from our
diet, so it comes in through
our intestines and can
be excreted in the feces.
Calcium can also be
excreted by the kidneys,
through the urine, and
it can be stored in bone.
We have a lot of calcium
actually stored
within our bones.
When we're in
homeostasis, all these
rates of calcium
released and uptake
from the bones and
excretion are equal.
So there's no net
change in the ECF.
Going into a little
bit more detail about
how calcium is handled
within the body.
In the GI tract, there's
a wide range of how
much active calcium
reabsorption there is.
Mainly this is done
through TRPV6. So that's
transcellular transient
receptor potential valenoid
6. And that's the
channel in the apical
membrane of duodenum and
proximal to the jejunum.
So that's really
how in the GI tract,
we're going to actively
uptake calcium.
Passively, it's about 5%, so
it's not critically important.
It's part of the power cellular
mechanism throughout
the intestine.
bone is almost where all
the calcium is stored
in the body about 99
percent osteoclasts are
going to reabsorb
calcium from the bone and
increase calcium levels
take calcium away from
balloons osteoblasts are
going to decrease calcium
by building bone and
storing calcium there
moving on to calcium
handling we're only going
to talk about ionized so
that's the non-protein
balance of calcium which
is about 45 as we said
before is filtered almost
all that is going to be
reabsorbed in the proximal
tubule and that's going to
be passive in conjunction
with sodium in the thick
ascending loop of henley
that is again going to be
passive and that's going
to be a paracellular
mechanism involving clodin
-16. In the distal nephron,
only 15% is reabsorbed,
and that's the most
physiologically important calcium
regulation and dysregulation
in disease states. And
that's because that is
where the active calcium
reabsorption takes place.
And this is the result
of calcium entering
the tubular cells
via TRPV5, the
transient receptor
potential valenoid 5.
So again, this distal
nephron is where
the active calcium
regulation takes place.
Moving on from calcium
handling, we're going to talk
about how the calcium regulates,
how the body regulates
calcium via these different
sites within our system.
One of the main ways and one
of the clinically important
ways is through the parathyroid
gland and parathyroid
hormone parathyroid hormone
as the name suggests is
secreted by the parathyroid
gland the way that works
is that the parathyroid senses
calcium or senses changes
in the ionized calcium in
the plasma via the calcium
sensing receptor on the
parathyroid cells so the calcium
sensing receptor is going
to view any changes in
the ionized calcium concentration
one way or the other.
The body wants to keep
that concentration
level and the same,
and it's going to
regulate the calcium by
increasing or decreasing
calcium throughout
the body to do so.
So how does the
parathyroid hormone work?
Parathyroid hormone is
going to increase plasma
calcium at the end of the
day. This is going to be done
through the intestines
the bones and the kidneys
so all different sites we
were talking about before
in the intestines
parathyroid hormone is
going to promote
renal formation of 125
dihydroxide vitamin
d which is going to
enhance calcium
reabsorption in the bones
parathyroid hormone is going
to increase osteoclastic
activity to reabsorb calcium
from the bones and increase
plasma calcium and finally
in the kidneys we're
going to see an increase in
the distal nephron reabsorption
through TRPV5. As we
noted before, that's the
active mechanism by which
the kidneys regulate calcium.
Vitamin D also plays
a really important
role in maintaining
calcium within the body.
In the intestines, vitamin
D increases calcium
absorption via expression
of TRPV6. In the bones, it's
an unclear mechanism that,
again, will increase calcium
reabsorption in the
kidneys we see reabsorption
of the calcium in the
distal convoluted tubule and
collecting duct via tier
pv5 so again as this picture
is showing the right side
vitamin d is playing an
important role in all
these sites finally calcium
self-regulates as well the
way this happens is there's
calcium sensing receptors
throughout the nephron
which can sense calcium and
either increase excretion
or reabsorption to correct
calcium levels within
the body let's move on and
talk about hypercalcemia
hypercalcemia obviously meaning
calcium concentrations
are elevated
90 of the time this
is going to be due to
primary hyperparathyroidism
or malignancy
We can have
hyperparathyroidism, which
results in excess
PTH production.
Primary hyperparathyroidism is
the most common one of these.
And the reason that
primary hyperparathyroidism
happens is typically due
to a parathyroid adenoma.
The parathyroid
adenoma increases
parathyroid hormone levels.
Parathyroid hormone
increases calcium.
Thus, we get hypercalcemia.
Secondary hyperparathyroidism,
we usually don't see
hypercalcemia. We actually
see a normal or low
calcium level. That's why
you don't see it on here.
And that happens because
secondary hypercalcemia
is usually due to chronic
kidney disease. So when
we have chronic kidney
disease, the parathyroid
gland will compensate by
increasing the amount of
parathyroid hormone due to a
lack of a renal reabsorption,
which we'll talk about
a little bit later.
Rarely, you can
see hypercalcemia
from a tertiary
hyperparathyroidism.
This happens in someone
who had a secondary
hyperparathyroidism, they
get kidney transplant.
So, you know, clearly
a less common cause.
What happens is you get
hyperplasia of the parathyroid
gland and secondary
hyperparathyroidism. And then
once the kidneys are working
fine again from the kidney
transplant, you wind up
getting too much calcium.
Another reason we see excess
PTH production causing
hypercalcemia is ectopic
PTH secretion, also rare. So
usually if we're seeing
excess PTH production in the
setting of hypercalcemia, it's
going to be due to primary
hyperparathyroidism. Just
mentioning the tertiary
and the ectopic PTH secretion
for completeness sake.
Malignancy, the other
cause which makes
up 90% of hypercalcemia
etiologies.
So obviously important
to know about malignancy.
Usually, this is going
to be due to solid
tumors. And what we
see is secretion of
parathyroid hormone
-related protein, or PTHRP.
So PTHRP, we get suppressed
PTH levels and high calcium.
The PTH-related protein
serves to increase calcium,
and therefore the
parathyroid gland is going to
naturally lower the amount
of PTH in response to
that, because there's
already high calcium levels.
Another common cause of
hypercalcemia for malignancy
is lytic bone lesions or
lytic bone metastases.
A lot of times this is going to
happen from multiple myeloma.
And again, we're
going to see decreased
parathyroid hormone because
the calcium levels are
high. The parathyroid
gland is working
properly. So it's not going
to make more parathyroid
hormone because calcium
is already high.
And the picture on the
right is squamous cell
carcinoma of the lung
squamous cell carcinoma of the
lung is one of the more
common causes of pth related
protein being produced
so it's important to know
there are other causes of
hypercalcemia again less
common is 90 percent or from
primary hyperparathyroidism
and malignancy we can
have excess vitamin d
D, excess vitamin D, a
common etiology of that
is sarcoidosis. In
sarcoidosis, you get
increased endogenous
production of 125 vitamin D.
That is more common
than people taking
too much of vitamin
D supplementation.
Again, with
hypervitaminosis D, you get
low PTH because the
parathyroid gland
is sensing the increased
calcium levels.
We can have hypercalcemia
from excess calcium
intake in the form of
milk alkali syndrome. This
is typically when
someone's having too much
calcium carbonate, which
is what we see in Tums.
So if you're having a
patient who has heartburn and
they're taking Tums all day,
you're going to get a lot
of calcium carbonate,
increased calcium levels too
high. Again, the parathyroid
hormone is going to be
low because the parathyroid
gland is working properly.
Lastly, we can
see increased bone
reabsorption. This
typically happens
from immobilization
or hyperthyroidism,
not hyperparathyroid,
hyperthyroidism. in.
Both these cases will cause
PTH below in response.
How would this look clinically
for a patient with
hypercalcemia?
First, in our lab drawer,
we're going to see an
elevated total calcium
level. Now I say total
calcium because this includes
the albumin bound portion
in addition to the free
ionized calcium. So we
can correct for that. If
albumin is low, typically
below 4.1, we add some
calcium to our value we
receive. If albumin is
very high, we reduce the
calcium level. There's a
formula. It's not important
to memorize right now
just to know about it.
In patients who have mild
hypercalcemia, meaning
11 to 11.5 milligrams
per deciliter, usually
they're going to be
asymptomatic. When we get
to moderate hypercalcemia
between 12 and 14.
You get some nonspecific
symptoms, fatigue,
muscle pain, aches,
muscle weakness, severe
hypercalcemia. You
typically get your
neuropsychiatric symptoms
like depression, anxiety.
Cognitively, they
can be impaired,
so some impaired
memory, confusion.
Even comas can result as
we get to higher levels gi
wise patients are often
going to be constipated we
can get peptic ulcer
disease or anorexia in the
kidneys we can get nephrolithiasis
or kidney stones you
can also get renal
insufficiency and from a
cardiovascular perspective
perspective we see short qt
intervals and bradycardia
once we have an actual high
calcium level we're trying
diagnose our patients
we can look at this diagnostic
algorithm here so we
have hypercalcemia first
thing we're going to do is
measure parathyroid hormone
right so when we measure
parathyroid hormone it's
either going to be high
or low if we have an elevated
pth in the setting of
hypercalcemia it's
almost always going
to be primary
hyperparathyroidism
Now, if we have high
calcium and low PTH,
we want to measure
some other components.
So we want to look at
pyrothyroid-related hormone,
PTHRP. We want to check vitamin
D levels as well. If you
see an elevated PTHRP in
hypercalcemia and a low PTH,
that's most likely going
to be malignancy. If
we see an elevated
calcidiol, that's probably
going to be due to an
increased intake of calcium
or vitamin D, so like
milk alkali syndrome.
If we see elevated calcitriol,
like the sarcoidosis
we talked about before,
we get ectopic production
of 125 vitamin D.
If none of these three
are elevated, usually it's
going to be lytic
metastases from something
like multiple lieloma or
other rare causes that you
don't need to be concerned
about at this time.
How do we treat
hypercalcemia? If it's mild to
moderate, we would just
avoid the aggravating
factors if possible and
provide adequate hydration.
So, for instance,
some factors that
aggravate hypercalcemia
would be high
calcium in your diet
which makes sense
thiazide diuretics can
result in or worsen
hypercalcemia and hydration
is key because of kidney
stones and kidney stone
prevention through hydration
when we get side severe
hypercalcemia we want
to start giving iv fluids
so four to six liters
of normal saline in the
in the first 24 hours.
We want to give a good
amount of fluids to the
patient, the reason
being is that if we have
hypovolemia, it's going to
exacerbate hypercalcemia
by impairing the renal
clearance of calcium. So
when we maintain adequate
fluid levels, we're
helping the body clear
calcium through the kidneys.
Bisphosphonates, like
zoledronic acid, have a role
here. That's because they
inhibit bone osteoclast
-mediated reabsorption of
calcium, so we're inhibiting
bone reabsorption through
the bisphosphonates.
Glucocorticoids play
a role by decreasing
125 vitamin D production
within the body.
The reason that's important
is because vitamin
D helps to increase
calcium levels. So
glucocorticoids are
going to decrease vitamin
D and therefore help
to decrease calcium.
As always, the ultimate
way to treat with any
problem is to deal with
the underlying cause. So
treat the malignancy going
on once the patient is
stabilized, if they have
severe hypercalcemia.
For hyperparathyroidism, we
can do a parathyroidectomy,
especially if the
patient's symptomatic.
Moving on, let's talk about
high O-calcemia or low
calcium levels there's two
different sets of etiologies
we can break it down into
those with low parathyroid
hormone or those with high
starting with low hypoparathyroid
hormone this is usually
going to be due to
hypoparathyroidism commonly
this is going to be a result
of surgery after surgical
removal of the thyroid or
next surgery where we get
destruction of the gland or
patients can have antibodies
to the pyrothyroid gland
or calcium sensing receptors
so these antibodies will
render ineffective so one
way or another we're getting
destruction or the parathyroid
gland not working at
all we can have radiation
to the parathyroid gland
hemochromatosis and wilson's
disease so different storage
diseases can result in damage
to the parathyroid gland
which ultimately cause
hypoparathyroidism abnormal
gland development is another
possible etiology for
hypoparathyroidism, which
are usually due to genetic
defects, or we can have altered
regulation of parathyroid
hormone, so impaired
processing of PTH. If we have
high PTH in the setting of
hypocalcemia, usually this
is going to be due to
secondary hyperparathyroidism.
So the PTH here is going to
be increased in these set
of etiologies in response
to low serum calcium. So the
issue here is not with the
parathyroid gland itself.
So the fact that we're
having high PTH and low
calcium means the
parathyroid gland and
parathyroid hormone are
working as it should be.
The parathyroid gland
is sensing low calcium
and responding by
increasing PTH levels.
So the issue is somewhere
else in the body.
So one of these reasons
could be vitamin D
deficiency or vitamin D
resistance. So deficiency,
obviously not getting
enough vitamin D. A
lot of patients need to
take supplementation.
Vitamin D resistance
via increased metabolism
to inactive metabolites
of vitamin D.
Renal insufficiency can
cause impairment in the
making of 125-dihydroxy
vitamin D production. So
that's something clinically
important. We can also
have parathyroid hormone
resistance syndrome. So this
is pseudo-hypoparathyroidism.
This usually presents
in childhood we get an
elevated pth but the
organs are not responsive
to the pth being produced
so really the body is
resisting the parathyroid
hormone we can have extra
vascular deposition of
calcium this is usually
going to happen when we
have osteoblastic metastases
to bone so most commonly
in terms of cancers with
osteoblastic metastases
usually this is breast
and prostate cancer.
In severe tissue
injury, we can also have
this where we get
hypocalcemia and high PTH.
So these would be in
the setting of sepsis,
rhabdomyolysis, burns,
and really the mechanism
here is we get calcium
sequestration in tissues.
For patients experiencing
hypocalcemia,
we can see a few
clinical manifestations.
We can see tetany,
muscle cramps,
perioral paresthesias,
laryngospasm,
focal or generalized seizures.
Trousseau and Chovestek
signs are important.
Trousseau's is carpal
spasm, which we get
when we inflate a blood
pressure cuff to 20
millimeters of mercury
above the patient's
systolic blood pressure
for three minutes.
Chovestek sign is going
to be contraction of the
ipsilateral ****** muscles
elicited by tapping
the ****** nerve. That's
just inferior to the ear.
There's a good
video here via this
link from New
England Journal of
Medicine. I encourage
you to look at it.
Please click on the
link, take a look,
and it'll demonstrate
how it actually
looks realistically
clinically for you.
Patients can also
present with seizures and
severe hypocalcemia,
cardiovascular effects.
So, as we know before,
in hypercalcemia, we get
short QT and bradycardia.
In hypocalcemia, as in
this, we got the opposite.
So, we got long QT.
We can wind up with
Tosadepois, which
can turn into a
ventricular tachycardia.
We can also get some
papillodina in patients,
which is optic disc swelling.
All these can result
from hypocalcemia.
Here's a table showing
some more common causes
of hypocalcemia and
the lab values that you
would expect to see in
those different instances.
If we look at hypoparathyroidism,
which is going to
be the most common reason
we have low PTH in the
setting of hypocalcemia,
we obviously have a low
calcium, we get an elevated
phosphate, which we'll
talk about a little bit more
in the next part of this
lecture, because parathyroid
hormone serves to
increase calcium and decrease
phosphate. So low PTH,
the opposite is happening
here. Everything else
would be normal. Another
reason we can have normal
to low PTH and high blood
calcemia, which we didn't
talk about yet, but we
will talk about later in
this lecture, would be the
setting of low magnesium.
For our cases of elevated
PTH, We could see vitamin
D deficiency, where we
have low normal calcium,
elevated PTH, and a low
25-hydroxyvitamin D, not
consuming enough vitamin
D here, most likely, as
opposed to chronic kidney
disease, where we would
see the same elevated PTH
and low calcium. However,
the 125-dihydroxyvitamin
D, the one
produced in the
kidney, is not working.
So in CKD, it's a
kidney dysfunction where
we see the 125
-dihydroxyvitamin D not working
with an elevated
creatinine, which would be
pretty indicative of
a kidney dysfunction.
Pseudohypoparathyroidism,
we talked about earlier,
in pseudohypoparathyroidism,
we'll sell an
elevated PTH level
and elevated phosphate
level with a low calcium
and normal creatinine,
normal vitamin D,
and normal magnesium.
Treatment-wise,
mild hypocalcemia,
we're going to give oral
calcium supplementation
and vitamin D3.
Oral calcium supplementation
is usually 1,500 to 2
,000 milligrams of calcium
daily, and vitamin D is 50
,000 international units
weekly for six to eight weeks.
Severe hypocalcemia or
symptomatic hypocalcemia,
we're going to give IV
calcium at first, then switch
to oral. We want to
correct any concurrent
electrolyte abnormalities
such as hypomagnesemia. If
you have a patient who
has hypopyrathyroidism or
the destruction of the
parathyroid gland or something
else causing the
parathyroid gland, they need
lifelong calcium and
vitamin D supplementation.
Moving on from calcium,
let's talk about phosphate.
So some things to
know about phosphate
handling, 85% of phosphate
is in the bone mineral.
So just like calcium,
the majority of it
is stored in bone. In
the small intestine,
via sodium-dependent
independent pathways
that may involve
vitamin D regulation,
the sodium-independent
pathways appear
unregulated and may
explain robust absorption
of phosphate in
patients with vitamin
D deficiency in
advanced kidney disease.
Bone phosphates are regulated
via osteoblasts an osteoclast.
FGF23,
which is fibroblast
growth factor 23, may also
be involved in mobilizing
phosphate from bone.
Renally, in the
proximal tubule, we have
three transport
proteins dependent on
countercurrent sodium
transport, so type 2A, 2C,
and type 3 sodium
phosphate co-transporters.
The way the body regulates
how much phosphate we
have is by the rate of
renal tubular absorption.
The intestines are very
efficient at absorbing phosphate
and calcium into the body.
So kidneys are really
where the body regulates
how much phosphate we have.
The fractional excretion
of phosphate is actually
about 10 to 15%. So reabsorption
is really going to depend
on how much phosphate we
intake into the diet how
much the concentration in
the serum is phosphate power
thyroid hormone levels
vitamin d levels and fgf23
pth and fgf23 that's handled
through the reduction of
sodium phosphate co-transpo
co-transporters in the
kidney so pth and fgf23 are
going to reduce phosphate
reabsorption by reducing
those sodium phosphate co
-transporters So when we see
an elevated PTH and elevated
F2F23, we can expect that
phosphate would be lower.
Low intake of phosphate
and low siloamables are
generally going to cause
the opposite to occur.
So we're going to see
increased expression of
sodium phosphate co
-transporters in these cases.
And PTH is also
going to reabsorb
phosphate through the bone.
One key thing to keep
in mind is that the
parathyroid gland is
much more concerned
about regulating
calcium than phosphate.
So parathyroid hormone
increases calcium, decreases
phosphate, but calcium
is what the parathyroid
gland is going to be most
sensitive to. So if it
has to choose which one
it's going to regulate,
it's going to regulate
calcium more than phosphate.
Let's talk about some
etiologies of hypophosphatemia.
One main category of reasons
we can get hypophosphatemia
is from reduced renal
phosphate absorption.
So that's why I'll present
with hypophosphatemia. We're
not absorbing phosphate in
the kidney sufficiently.
One reason is primary and
secondary hyperparathyroidism.
So that increase in
parathyroid hormone,
we're going to see
decreased reabsorption of
phosphate in the kidney,
right? So PTH is going to
serve to increase calcium,
decrease phosphate.
In vitamin D deficiency,
we can get a secondary
hyperparathyroidism. So again,
we'll see increased PTH
having the same effect.
Vitamin D deficiency
also, as I previously
mentioned, we might see some
decreased GI phosphate
absorption as well.
Phosphate wasting syndromes.
This is associated
with rickets and
osteomalacia. As you
might recall, rickets
is characterized by
craniosynostosis, a lot
of pain within the bone,
pseudofractures
in short stature,
as well as hypophosphatemia.
Fanconi syndrome is an
impairment of proximal
tubular function and
wasting of urinary compounds
reabsorbed there, so glucose,
calcium, and phosphate.
Another category of
disorders of hypophosphatemia
is caused by decreased
intestinal absorption.
So like I mentioned, there's
little regulation
of gut absorption
and the little is
controlled by vitamin D. So
if someone had inadequate
intake, such as if
they had prolonged severe
phosphate deprivation,
more often poor intake
and chronic diarrhea.
It would have to be
one or most likely a
combination of the two to
cause hypophosphatemia.
Antacids that have aluminum
or magnesium can cause
decreased intestinal
absorption of phosphate.
It causes a net
loss of phosphate
via aluminum and
magnesium salts.
Ceratorrhea or chronic
diarrhea, we get decreased
phosphate absorption
in the gut as well.
Finally, the last
category of causes of
hypophosphatemia that we
can break it down into are
reasons of phosphate
shifting into the cell. This
can happen when we have
increased insulin secretion.
So if you have an
underlying phosphate
depletion during refeeding
syndrome, So after
prolonged starvation and
people start to eat again,
severe hypophosphatemia can
actually occur. And this
is because the shift of
phosphate into the cells
of the body by producing
insulin in response to
that glucose. So again,
increased insulin secretion.
Also, someone is experiencing
respiratory alkalosis,
the high pH can cause
a shift of phosphate
into the cells, resulting
in hypophosphatemia.
So how would
patients present who
are suffering from
hypophosphatemia?
Well, all these
manifestations are going to
be caused as a result
of depletion of ATP.
So we need phosphate
for energy within our
body, which is ATP is
the main source of that.
so in the cns patients
can have seizures delirium
or even coma cardiovascularly
we can see decreased
myocardial contractility
patients can have mis
and even ventricular
arrhythmias we can see damage
to both skeletal and
smooth muscles patients can
suffer from dysphagia
rhabdomyolysis breakdown of
muscle can ensue in this
case patients will get a
characteristic red or
brown urine which is what
you're seeing on the right
-hand side of your screen.
Hemodologic consequences
can also happen. So you
can get erythrocyte rigidity
and actually reduction
of phagocytosis from
the white blood cells.
Diagnosis and treatment.
The way you're
going to determine
if someone has
hypophosphatemia is by a
24-hour urine excretion.
If there is less
than 100 milligrams,
This is going to be
telling us that there's
internal redistribution
or decreased intestinal
absorption. If there's above
100 milligrams, that means
there's reduced renal
phosphate absorption
because the kidneys are
not working properly in
keeping phosphate when we
have low serum phosphate.
Treatment, if they're
asymptomatic or symptomatic
with a slightly reduced
phosphate level, we're
going to give oral therapy
if they're symptomatic
and their phosphate's
less than one then
we're going to give iv
therapy hyperphosphatemia
again one category is due
to issues with the kidney
so instead of increased
reabsorption or decrease
your absorption, we see
increased excretion of
phosphate by the kidneys
as one group of etiologies.
This can happen with
hypoparathyroidism.
So, deficient parathyroid
hormone secretion is
going to increase renal
phosphate absorption and
decrease calcium absorption.
And this is going
to happen via increased
expression of those sodium
phosphate co-transporters.
We can see parathyroid
suppression. So
again, low parathyroid
hormone, this can happen
from vitamin D deficiency,
vitamin A overdoses,
or milk alkaline syndrome.
Renal insufficiency.
So any sufficient
reduction in the glomerular
filtration rate causes
phosphate retention. In
patients with acromegaly, we
can see hyperphosphatemia.
This is presumably through
insulin-like growth
factors. Patients with
acromegaly characteristically
have ****** features,
like you see on the
right, enlargement of
the brow, nose, and jaw.
In familial tumoral calcinosis,
rare autosomal recessive
disorder, you don't really
have to worry about too
much for our purposes.
Patients can have
an acute phosphate
load causing hyperphosphatemia.
This happens when there's a
tumor lysis syndrome, which
is a large tumor burden
that's being broken down,
usually in response to
radiation or chemotherapy, and
this releases a large amount
of phosphate, potassium,
and uric acid. In rhabdomyolysis,
you get damaged muscle
cells that can release
myoglobin and phosphate, and
we get that characteristic
dark urine we talked about.
Patients suffering
from exogenous
phosphate intake, this
is usually going to
happen in phosphate
-containing enemas.
As you might expect,
clinically for these patients,
we can see tetany and
a presentation that
otherwise be similar
to hypocalcemia, right?
Because those typically,
they go together. So
tetany, seizures, renal
failure in patients,
cardiac arrhythmia is
going to be present. You
can get pulmonary and
cardiac calcification,
such as you see on the
right-hand side. This
is actually a metastatic
calcification of the
alveolar septa in a
renal dialysis patient.
There's not a ton of
great therapeutic options
in the acute setting. We
want to volume expand our
patients to promote renal
phosphate clearance.
Antacids can be helpful
causing chelation and
helpful limiting
absorption of the kidneys.
Hemodialysis is the most
effective, and this is what
should be considered early
for patients with severe
hypophosphatemia especially
those with renal failure and
symptomatic associated
hypocalcemia let's go to some
questions an 88 year old male
presents the ed unconscious
while taking his blood
pressure you notice carpal
spasm which the following
is the most likely diagnosis
you should be thinking
hypocalcemia the
reason being you're
noticing carpal spasm right?
So that should be
triggering your head
trousseau's sign, which
we discussed earlier.
Now we have the same
patient and we get back
some lab results. Calcium
is one milligram per
deciliter. Phosphate
is 13 milligrams per
deciliter. Parathyroid
hormones is 94.3 nanometers
per liter 25 hydroxy
vitamin d is normal bun
is 10 creatinine is 1.0
what's the most likely
diagnosis here the answer
would be pth resistance
syndrome so we should
understand why that is
based on the laboratory
results right so first of
all we have hypocalcemia
and hyperphosphatemia
as well as an increase in
pth right so let's go through
our choices if we had
primary hyperparathyroidism
we would see an elevated
pth which we would
expect to cause high calcium
and low phosphate not
the other way around
vitamin d deficiency we
know this is incorrect
because vitamin d levels
are normal chronic
kidney disease again not
correct because we see
bun and creatin are normal
Squamous cell carcinoma
lung is associated
with an increase in
parathyroid hormone-related
protein, which would
cause hypercalcemia.
This is actually parathyroid
hormone resistance,
and that's where we
have sufficient thyroid
hormone being produced, but
the body is not responding
to it at the receptor
level appropriately.
So it looks like a picture
of hypoparathyroidism.
let's go to another question
a 55 year old female
presents to the emergence
partner with anxiety
constipation abdominal pain
on cat scan the abdomen
is found to have
nephrolithiasis which of the
following is most likely
metabolic abnormality
the correct answer here
is hypophosphatemia
now it could also look
like hypercalcemia
because those usually
go hand in hand like
we said but that's
not one of our options
Getting the patient's
laboratory measurements,
calcium is high at 14
.3, phosphate is low
at 1, parathyroid hormone
is low, parathyroid
hormone-related peptide
is 3.8, which is high,
125-dihydroxyvitamin
D is the normal range.
So what is the most
likely diagnosis here?
The most likely
diagnosis is going to
be squamous cell
carcinoma in the lung.
You should be able to go
through these other answer
choices and figure out
why, but essentially we
have an elevated PTHRP,
which we talked about would
act similarly to parathyroid
hormone and increasing
calcium and decreasing
phosphate, and that's
associated with squamous
cell carcinoma in the lung.
Finally, let's talk
about magnesium.
Magnesium forms a key
complex with ATP, so
a really important
phosphate as well, and
it's crucial for
neuromuscular activity.
The body closely regulates
the range between
0.7 to 1 millimoles
within the extracellular
fluid. Almost all
of it is within the
cells or bones. In a
healthy individual,
total magnesium is kept
constant by interactions
throughout the intestines,
bone, and kidneys.
Dietary, antique,
fecal excretion,
reabsorption in the blood
from the kidneys, urinary
output, muscle, and
other tissues, usually
bone playing a key
role in our magnesium
stores within the body.
About 30 to 40% of
magnesium is going
to be absorbed in
the intestines,
specifically in the jejunum
and ileum. And this is
stimulated by 125-dihydroxyvitamin
D, but it's regulated
again by the kidney. So 70
% of magnesium is absorbed
through the thick ascending
loop of Henle. 20% is in
the proximal tubule and 10
% is in the distal tubule.
In the thick ascending
limb of the kidney, it's a
passive function via
favorable electron gradient
generated by reabsorption
of sodium potassium chloride
from the sodium potassium
2 chloride transport.
And this is facilitated
by junctional proteins
clotting 16 and clotting
19 we can see decreased
reabsorption with hypercalcemia
or hypermagnesemia
the distal convoluted
tubule is important
for fine-tuning
of our potassium
or magnesium regulation
hypermagnesemia
etiologies one category is
intestinal causes so
diarrhea vomiting, although
diarrhea is more common.
So malabsorption,
stratorrhea, chronic
diarrhea, and even acute
diarrhea can all result
in hypomagnesemia.
Proton pump inhibitors
can cause hypomagnesemia.
The presumed mechanism
is impaired absorption
of magnesium by the
intestinal epithelial cells.
Primary intestinal
hypomagnesemia, it's a
familial disorder
that's rare, and then
hypomagnesemia with
secondary hypocalcemia.
And this is caused by
mutation in the gene
encoding TRPM6, protein
that along with TRPM7 forms
a channel that's important
for intestinal and
distal tubular renal
transcellular magnesium
transport. So more
commonly, we're to see it in
diarrhea, vomiting, and
proton pump inhibitors.
We can also have renal causes
of hypomagnesemia. This
is usually due to renal
losses. It can happen from
genetic wasting syndromes
like Gittleman syndrome, which
is an autosomal recessive
mutation in the thiazide
-sensitive sodium chloride co
-transporter, and it's associated
with hypocalcinuria we
can also see it in border
syndrome in the sodium potassium
2 chloride transport more
commonly we could see this
with medications so your
loop thiazide diuretics
these are going to inhibit
magnesium absorption nephrotoxic
drugs can cause urinary
magnesium wasting this
can be amino glycosides or
amphotericin b tubular
dysfunctions like acute tubular
necrosis uncontrolled diabetes
probably due to osmotic
diuresis and hypercalcemia
so this might be secondary to
hyperparathyroidism also
due to calcium and magnesium
competing for transport and
thick sending lupatenly how
do we see
hypomagnesemia manifest
well a few different ways
neurologically we can see
weakness tremors tetany
so similar to what you
might see in hypocalcemia.
Cardiovascular, we
can see widened QRS,
widened PR and
arrhythmia, specifically
torsade de poix, which
is what's pictured here,
translated loosely as
circling the drain.
Key thing to keep in mind,
typically it's going to
be difficult to describe
clinical manifestations
solely to magnesium.
As we mentioned, it plays
an important role in
phosphate and calcium as
well, so we can see these
kind of mixed up with each
other and intermingling.
Diagnosis and treatment.
If there's no
apparent etiology,
check magnesium
excretion. Usually, we're
treating this by
repletion with either oral
or IV magnesium,
depending on the severity.
IV magnesium, clearly,
if we're having the
ventricular arrhythmia
of Tostate de Croix, and
you want to correct any
concurrent deficiencies
in other things like
phosphate and calcium go
to a question
talking about hypermagnesemia
for a minute so which
of the following are the
expected manifestations
of hypermagnesemia correct
answer is all the above
most prominent clinical
manifestations of hypermagnesemia
or vasodilation
neuromuscular blockade and
when this happens serum
magnesium concentrations are
above tilling two millimoles
per liter we can also
get hypotension that's
refractory to vasopressors
or volume expansion and
that could be an early sign
patients also get nausea
lethargy and weakness that
can progress to respiratory
failure we can have
patients with hypoactive
tendon reflexes when we get
serum magnesium levels
greater than four millimoles.
And other findings
include GI hypomotility or
ileus, ****** flushing,
and pupillary dilation.
What are cardiac
complications we
would expect with
hypermagnesemia?
So in hypermagnesemia, we
can actually see paradoxical
bradycardia. So the
opposite of what we see with
the ventricular tachycardia
of hypomagnesemia. We can
get heart black and at
certain magnesium levels,
they're approaching four
millimoles per liter asystole.
So in summary, you should
be able, after watching
and reviewing this lecture,
to outline calcium,
phosphate, magnesium
regulation, dyslexic regulation.
Lower down on the
slide are some core
references and please
feel free to give
me any feedback
via the link below.
Thank you so much for
your time and attention.